New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Records 1991.0009
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
- Record Group 1: Secretary's Records, undated, 1760-1971
  - Series I: Old Company Secretary Files, Bulk, 1930-1945; undated, 1840-1947
    - [13-13.5] Board of Directors memoranda: income account and selected statistics; financial information; income and revenue; maps: railroad lines; photos of coaches (exterior); newspaper articles; article: "McClellon Water-Tube Boiler Test", 1917-1952 (Box 19)
    - [13.6-13.16] Trustees Meetings: memoranda to and from Board of Directors, railroad accidents and fatalities; passenger and freight service; revenue and statistics; airline travel: rates and routes; company's coal situation; Springfield Street Railroad Co.: revenue, 1920-1952 (Box 20)
    - [13.17-13.35] Trustees Meetings: memoranda from Trustees; timetable changes; equipment situation; fire damage on Cos Cob bridge (1939); overnight freight service (Speed Witch); probable effect of the war in Europe on railroad business (1939); operation of daily coach service between Washington D.C. and Maine (train named "East Wind"); flood and hurricane destruction (1938, 1944, 1950); freight traffic; ticket sales to travel groups; low and nonpaying passenger trains; limited train statistics; bus vs. train service; passenger service in various cities; maps: Old Colony Railroad lines, 1931-1951 (Box 21)
    - [13.36-13.68] Memoranda from Trustees, Board of Directors, Stockholders, Special Committee on pensions; pensions; payroll; rail failures; revocable permit, authority for expenditure, operating and traffic statistics; proposed new train service, automobile travel, various railroad companies, information on Freedom Train, 1902-1949 (Box 22)
    - [15.58-.60] Letters authorizing pensions and dollar amounts; statements of authorized pension payroll
      - 1902-1935 (Box 23)
      - 1918-1946 (Box 24)
      - 1917-1947 (Box 25)
    - [37-37.8] Memoranda to and from Board of Directors, Stockholders: Stockholder meeting ballots Federal decree: complaint; petitions, news releases; By-laws, charters; Boston and Maine Railroad, Boston Holding Co., Eastern Steamship Corp., 1907-1935 (Box 26)
    - [37.8-37.40] Memoranda from Board of Directors, Stockholders, Committees; Federal decree: US v. NYNH&H; Bill of complaints; petitions, bus and railway revenue; news releases; releases; Connecticut Company: sale; income account, 1905-1933 (Box 27)
    - [41-44] Memoranda from Trustees, Stockholders, Board of Directors Meetings: real estate transactions, maps, Public Utilities Commission (CT) docket; Meeting memoranda: Northern Railroad, Pemigewasset Valley Railroad, Wilton Railroad, Connecticut and Passumipsic Railroad, Peterboro Railroad, Kansas, Oklahoma and Gulf Railwa y, Springfield Railway Company, Atchinson, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway Co., 1914-1951 (Box 28)
    - [44.35-83] Memoranda from meetings of Board of Directors, Trustees, Stockholders, Committee on New Haven Station; real estate transactions; insurance policies; blueprints, building licenses and permits; Public Utilities Commission dockets, annual reports of New Haven Police Department, Cedar Hill Yard, 1911-1947 (Box 29)
    - [102-115] Memoranda from meetings of Stockholders, Board of Directors, Special Committee on Finance; expenditures for additions and improvements; report on maintenance of railroad; contracts for construction of equipment; Public Utilities Commission (CT) docket; Interstate Commerce Commission Act and its Amendment; Thames River Bridge dedication and engineer's report; Boston Terminal Co.; agreement and settlement between Director General of Railroads and NYNH&H, 1903-1967 (Box 30)
    - [115-133] Memoranda from Board of Directors: summary of net corporate income; proposed Hydro-electric development; receipts and disbursement of Equitable Trust Company of New York; Revenue Act collateral indentures; agreements, 1901-1928 (Box 31)
    - [133-147] Memoranda from meetings of Board of Directors, stockholders; petitions, decree, Public Utilities Commission of Connecticut dockets; real estate appraisal; statement of balance sheets and income account; record showing stock; ballots; debentures; legal cases; merger agreement: Consolidated Railway Company; agreements, 1901-1948 (Box 32)
    - [147, 181] Memoranda of Board of Directors, stockholders: bills of complaint, legal cases: Harold Norris, Edwin Adams, Bartlett; Registered Gold Bond Specimens; Reports covering destruction of cancelled European loan Franc debentures, 1910-1946 (Box 33)
    - [181] European loan; memoranda from Board of Directors; Office of Treasurer; list of bondholders, Committee on Stocklist; Interstate Commerce Commission finance docket; agreements; collateral trust indentures; Grand Central Terminal: leases, agreements, drawings, 1900-1947 (Box 34)
    - [202, 247] Grand Central Terminal: memoranda to Board of Trustees; lease; blueprints, Clayton Act: anti-trust questionnaires, NYNH&HRR and subsidiaries lines index, 1914-1963 (Box 35)
    - [247, 279, 289.1-.4, 290-292] Clayton Act: anti-trust questionnaires, NYNH&HRR and subsidiaries lines index; common and preferred stock; annual stockholders meeting, Memoranda from Board of Directors and Trustees; real estate appraisal and digests; Interstate Commerce Commission valuation dockets; Stockholders meeting, list of deeds of NYNHHRR (1840s-1900s); Norwich and Worcester Railroad; leases, contracts, agreements made by NYNH&H (c1840-1900), Publication of London Stock Exchange yearbooks; memoranda from Board of Trustees; blueprints, 1840-1955 (Box 36)
    - [294-321] Memoranda from Board of Directors, Trustees, Special and sub-committees on Finance, Stockholders; income accounts; finance dockets; Transportation Act; Railway mail payment; Corporate rent and sales of real estate; mortgages, creamation affadavit, 1914-1949 (Box 37)
    - [321] Memoranda from Board of Directors; petitions and court orders; By-laws of NYNH&H; Reorganization proceedings, ICC finance dockets mortgages; mortgage supplements and releases, 1920-1951 (Box 38)
    - [399.1-426] Memoranda from Stockholders and Board of Directors; repairs to cars; blueprints; New England Navigation Company, 1893-1945 (Box 39)
    - [595.38-595.70] Memoranda from Board of Directors; trucking, agreements and contracts, ICC finance dockets; insurance; blueprints; reports on old freight equipment; condemnation of equipment; leases; mortgages; [595.58] American Locomotive Company conditional sale agreement; Lina-Hamilton conditional sale agreement; Fairbanks, Morse & Company agreement; retirement of box cars; [595.61-.70] Retirement of box cars and locomotives, 1889-1950 (Box 40)
    - [595] Memoranda from Trustees; condition and condemnation of equipment; report on freight equipment, 1942-1947 (Box 41)
    - [643.1-.19] Memoranda from Trustees, Board of Directors; United States Bankruptcy Act; ICC finance dockets; petitions: reorganization proceedings; maps, 1935-1947 (Box 42)
    - [643.20-.38] Memoranda from Trustees, Board of Directors; report to Trustees regarding contracts; study of contracts, agreements, leases; disbursement and purchasing contracts; real estate department revenue reports; [643.31] Intercorporate relations: report on costs of storing and serving motor vehicles, intercorporate billing, proposed billing against Springfield Street Railroad; material purchased for maintaining motor coaches; Berkshire Street Railway Company; [643.32] Reorganization lists of parties of records and interviews; [643.33] Treatment of securities under plan of reorganization; [643.34-.38] Memoranda from Trustees and Board of Directors; contracts; analysis of real estate; petitions: reorganization proceedings; list of road and equipment items retired, 1935-1949 (Box 43)
    - [643.39] Memoranda from Trustees meeting: severance study, estimated revenues and expenses, petition: reorganization proceedings; maps; analysis of LCL traffic; materials and supplies; passenger terminal for Boston; recapitulating studies; abandonment study of Boston group of the Old Colony Railroad;[[643.44] Memoranda of meeting and appointment of Trustees; list of meetings for Board of Directors, stockholders, committee on preparing plan of reorganization; statements of fees and expenses; claims for compensation for services during reorganization proceedings; ICC finance dockets; income account, 1935-1953 (Box 44)
    - [644] Trustees meetings: memoranda, dockets, land deeds
      - 1936-1937 (Box 45)
      - 1937-1938 (Box 46)
      - 1938-1939 (Box 47)
      - 1940-1943 (Box 48)
    - [644] Trustees meetings: memoranda, dockets, reports on new legal business, 1943-1944 (Box 49)
    - [644] Trustees meetings: memoranda, dockets, 1944-1945 (Box 50)
    - [644] Trustees meetings: memoranda, dockets, petitions, 1945-1947 (Box 51)
    - [645-645.12] Companies and Subsidiaries: Providence and Worcester Railroad Company, Norwich and Worcester Railroad, Chatham Railroad Company, Holyoke and Westfield Railroad Company, Boston and Providence Railroad, Naugatuck Railroad, Providence, Warren and Bristol Railroad, Housatonic Railroad, Dutchess County Railroad, New Haven and Northampton Railroad, Harlem River and Portchester Railroad, Boston and New York Air Line, Wood River Branch Narragansett Pier Railroad; memoranda; payment of income taxes and rentals under lease; analysis of earnings; reorganization proceedings; blueprints; ICC finance dockets; summary of accounts; [645.12] Yardmasters, Assistant Yardmasters, and Stationmasters: increase in wages, 1905-1947 (Box 52)
    - [658] Companies and subsidiaries: memoranda from Trustees meetings; construction of sidetracks; blueprints; supplies; real estate transactions; equipment rental; authority for expenditures; Public Utilities Commission (CT) docket; Manufacturers Realty Company, 1938-1947 (Box 53)
    - [658, 833, 966, 1006] Memoranda from Trustees meetings: companies and subsidiaries; authority of expenditures; Public Utilities Commission (CT) docket; installation of sidetracks, General railroad situation: memoranda from Trustees meetings; President Patrick McGinnis' reports, gross operating revenue and other financial information; New Haven Railroad Management semina; Seminar material on President Dwight D. Eisenhower's Cabinet Committee report on Transportation; Eastern railroad policies, 1942-1961 (Box 54)
    - Various histories: Hotel Barclay, Berkshire Street Railway Company, Hotel Biltmore, Hotel Commodore, Hotel Parklane, Providence Produce Warehouse Company, Hotel Roosevelt, Hotel Waldorf Astoria, New Haven Railroad, New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad; Origin and nature of NHRR certificates of interest, undated (Box 55)
  - Series II: New Company Secretary Files, Bulk, 1947-1961; undated, 1935-1971
    These are files of the Corporate Secretary during the "New Company" period following the 1947 reorganization. This series is organized and indexed in the same structure as the OLD COMPANY SECRETARY FILES. It, too, contains the meeting minutes of the Stockholders, Trustees, and Directors, information on employee relations and labor practices, real estate, insurance and finance. This series also contains information on wartime employment, the second reorganization and bankruptcy. Of particular interest are the "Historical Files"--reference files of the early days of the New Haven and its predecessors. This series, like the OLD COMPANY SECRETARY FILES, was retained in the original order used by the Secretary's office; the A numbers are similar to but do not mirror the Old Company A numbers. The series is best accessed by the index cards in conjunction with the listings.
  - Series III: Agreements, 1870-1971
    These are the legal agreements and other legally binding papers between the New Haven and other companies for the use of realty. The AGREEMENTS are arranged in chronological order and are numbered sequentially from 260 to 19520. A partial card index is available to access these agreements. The index is arranged alphabetically by name of the city or town of the property, the name of the property (where one exists), and the company with whom the agreement exists. Additional agreements concerning Grand Central Terminal (1848-1959), Mail, Baggage and Carriage (1889-1964), and Park Square property (1895-1959) are arranged at the end of this series. These agreements are not indexed in the card index.
  - Series IV: Appropriations, 1916-1948
    These records document the expenditures and acquisitions which improved the railroad. This series contains information on purchases, repairs to and extensions of rails, retirement of equipment, and agreements with other companies. Examples include increasing ton rating for electric locomotives (1917), the purchase of 20 Russian locomotives (1920) and eliminating rail crossings. These are numbered A-5. to 5.719. Listed with the APPROPRIATIONS are script agreements, agreements- equipment trust, and listings of the New Haven's securities. For documents on land acquisition see Series VI, REAL ESTATE; see also records from the COMPTROLLER'S DEPARTMENT and the ACCOUNTING DEPARTMENT for documents relating to the day-to-day financial expenditures.
  - Series V: Legal Records, Bulk, 1840-1940; 1760-1961
    This series is divided into three subseries: Charters and By-Laws, Legal Agreements and Mortgages and Leases. These records are apparently duplicates of documents found in other series and include documents that do not fit the "A" number scheme. The Charters and By-Laws, 1846-1953, contain materials relating to the incorporation and history of the New Haven and some of its subsidiary companies. The majority of charters and by-laws are from the late 19th and early 20th centuries only. The New Haven charters are listed first, followed by subsidiary companies, listed in alphabetical order by name of the company. The corporate histories, also in this subseries, are arranged separately from the corporate charters and by-laws. The Legal Agreements are mostly nineteenth century documents; these are arranged by type of document. The Mortgages and Leases document the leasing of track and facilities by and from other railroad companies such as the Berkshire Street Railway Company, New York Connecting Railway and the Stamford Railway Company. Documents include leases, agreements and indentures. In addition to the leases, there are records relating to various mortgage bonds and securities issued. The Mortgages and Leases are arranged alphabetically by name of the company.
  - Series VI: Real Estate, 1917-1968
    This series contains documents on real estate holdings and transactions of the New Haven. Included in this series are maps, property descriptions, deeds, valuations, easements (rights to use crossings), and some title claims. The REAL ESTATE documents are filed chronologically by date of transaction. Each document was assigned an "A-12" number by the Secretary's office, A-12. to 12.7675. The documents are accessed by a card index which is arranged alphabetically by location; the card index is not complete.
  - Series VII: First Reorganization, 1935-1947
  - Series VIII: Stocks, 1872-1951
    Scope and Contents
    These records concern the company's stock and debentures before and during the first bankruptcy and reorganization. The series is divided into three subseries: Stockholders, New England Stockholders, and Ledger Cards of Stockholders. Stockholders contains correspondence, lists of stockholders, and vouchers about the company stock; these are numbered A-79 to 79.2. New England Stockholders is listings of individuals who held either Preferred Stock, Common Stock, Convertible Indentures and General Mortgage Income Bonds; the listing covers only the New England area. Ledger Cards contains information on who owned Preferred Stock, Convertible Debentures, and Common Stock; brokers are also listed. The cards document when stocks were bought, their value, and when due. Most of the Ledger Cards date 1943-48 and were due in either 1947 or 1948.
  - Series IX: Subsidiary Companies, Bulk, 1943-1947; 1872-1951
    This series contains documents relating to subsidiary companies of the New Haven. The records are for the following companies:
    Railroads: Central New England Railway; Hartford Connecticut Western Railroad; New York Connecting Railroad; Providence, Warren Bristol Railroad; Western Shore Railway
    Street Railways/Motor Coach Lines: Berkshire Motor Coach Company; Berkshire Street Railway Company; Connecticut Company; Connecticut Railway Lighting Company; County Transportation Company; Interstate Limited Motor Coach; New York Stamford Railway Company; Soundview Transportation Company
    Other Companies: New England Steamship Company; New England Airlines Inc.
    These represent only a few of the subsidiaries owned by the New Haven. The SUBSIDIARY COMPANIES series contains the organization records of those companies listed. The documents include: bylaws, meeting minutes, legal papers, reorganization plans, reports to the Interstate Commerce Commission (ICC), and other types of documents. The records are arranged by type of operation (railroad, street railway/motor coaches, marine and airline), and within that, alphabetically by company name. See Appendix C for a detailed listing of this series. See also the BOUND VOLUMES (RG 7) and the ANNUAL REPORTS (RG 3) for additional records of New Haven Railroad subsidiary, predecessor and successor companies, as well as Series VII, SUBSIDIARY COMPANIES, in the ACCOUNTING DEPARTMENT (RG 5).
- Record Group 2: Trustee's Records, 1920-1980
  This record group documents the responsibilities and activities of the court-appointed Trustees, especially during the second reorganization period of the New Haven Railroad. After a period of financial difficulties in the late 1950's, the New Haven filed a petition for reorganization under Section 77 of the Bankruptcy Act. The petition was granted on 7 July 1961. The United States District Court, District of Connecticut, appointed three trustees: Richard Joyce Smith, William Johnson Kirk (appointed in July) and Harry William Dorrigan (appointed in August). Dorrigan served until his death in 1966. Smith and Kirk continued to serve as co-Trustees until 1969. In appointing the Trustees the court stated:
  "The case does not have as its sole or chief purpose the modification of the debt structure, but the actual survival of the New Haven Railroad as a system of transportation for passengers and freight. It will be the task of these men to develop and put into execution a formula designed to achieve this." (Memorandum of Decision on Appointment of Trustees. 26 July 1961.)
  The records in the TRUSTEES record group reflect the tasks assigned by the Court, that of overseeing financial matters, continuing daily operations, and dealing with state and federal agencies involved in reorganizing the Railroad. The records fall into four broad categories: information gathering, District Court proceedings, Interstate Commerce Commission (ICC) hearings on reorganization, and the Pennsylvannia and New York Central Merger.
  While some records from the first reorganization, 1935-48, do exist in this record group, it seems likely they were maintained as a reference source by the second reorganization's trustees. Records for the first reorganization are located in the SECRETARY and ACCOUNTING DEPARTMENT record groups. Note that the container lists provided do not include every file heading found in a particular box; the lists provide only a selected sampling of topics.
  The detailed description lists the contents for all of the boxes in Record Group 2, Series 1-5.
  - Series I: Publications and Reports, Bulk, 1935-1968; 1920-1980
    This series contains records of both the first and second reorganizations. The series is divided into two subseries: Studies and Reports and Bound Volumes. Studies and Reports contains financial and operational information, most of it from the period of the first reorganization. Bound Volumes consists of the printed reorganization proceedings before the U.S. District Court for both periods of reorganization; ICC hearing minutes concerning the Penn Central merger; and the transcripts of hearings before the United States District Court.
  - Series II: Trustees Files, Bulk, 1960-1970; 1920-1972
    This series is further divided into three subseries: Numerical Files, General Reference Files, and Six Month Claims Files.
    Numerical Files, 1920-72, contain correspondence, memos, studies and reports, arranged in numerical order, which cover a variety of subjects from abandonments to the ICC and reorganization. Included here is a numerical sequence identified as Richard Joyce Smith files (RJS-O). There is a card index available only for the first section of numerical files.
    The General Reference Files 1953-70, were used as a basic source of information on technical matters, public opinion, government intervention in the reorganization, and the impact on local service and stations. Many of these files are identified with Trustee Harry W. Dorrigan.
    Six Month Claims, 1953-68, deals with those claims presented for debts incurred within six months of reorganization. These files contain memos, correspondence and legal records (exhibits and affidavits).
  - Series III: Penn Central Merger, 1962-1975
    This series contains correspondence, memoranda, court records, statistical reports, studies and newspaper clippings dealing with the merger of the New Haven Railroad with the Penn Central. This material covers proceedings before the U.S. District Court and the Interstate Commerce Commission. In March of 1962, the Pennsylvania Railroad and New York Central Railroad filed with the ICC for permission to merge. In June, the Trustees of the New Haven Railroad filed a petition with the ICC for inclusion in that merger. The final Pennsylvania and New York Central merger was granted only on the condition that it include the New Haven Railroad. The merger was approved in April 1966 and executed in 1968. Penn Central Merger material is also available in other series of the TRUSTEES record group.
  - Series IV: General Counsel, 1961-1982
    This series contains the office files of the General Counsel, who reported to the Trustees. It is divided into three subseries: Subject Files, Merger Records, and J. W. Moore Records.
    The Subject Files, 1961-77, are alphabetically arranged general reference files on a variety of topics.
    The Merger Records, 1961-73, consist mainly of legal records, hearings and transcripts relating to the reorganization and merger.
    The final subseries, J.W. Moore Records, 1962-82, contains records maintained by Professor Moore of Yale Law School, who served as Counsel to the Trustees. Some material deals with the Penn Central's bankruptcy and the subsequent formation of Conrail.
  - Series V: Treasurer's files, 1960-1975
    Like other series in the TRUSTEES record group, the Treasurer's files deals principally with the New Haven reorganization and merger with the Penn Central. Most of the series consists of court transcripts and ICC hearing reports. A significant amount of material deals with the incorporation of the Penn Central and other northeastern railroads into Conrail.
- Record Group 3: Annual Reports, 1835-1976